Hello, everyone. Today, I will quickly do one of the problems from the large group tutorial
here. So, the problem that we are doing today focuses on something called the induction hypothesis
generalisation. So, when you're doing mathematical induction and your induction hypothesis is not
strong enough to be applied, how can you strengthen it or generalise it? So, let me just remind you
of mathematical induction and how we use it and then tell you the problem. So, let me just recall
that to prove that a property P with natural numbers n, we prove two things. We have to prove two things,
right? The first one is that the property holds for zero, okay? Base case. And the second case
is that if you know that the property holds for number n from that, you can show that the
property holds for number n plus 1, which in our terminology will be that the property holds for
the successor of n, okay? So, that is proof by a mathematical induction is like that.
And we call this the induction hypothesis, okay? Let me also make a small remark, which is that
try to prove, if you want to prove something by induction, a theorem by mathematical induction,
use that schema or that rule, which is that in order to prove P, you have to prove P of zero
and this second goal or that schema or that rule or that recipe as mechanically as possible,
as mechanically as you can. What does that mean? That is to say, identify the P you are proving.
That's step number one. Step number two, apply the schema. Step number three, see if you can
use the induction hypothesis, the goal, to prove the step case. You have two cases. If yes,
then that's fine. If no, then try to find a more general P. Let's call it P prime. And then
go to step two, okay? Usually this thing, this step here, or this second branch,
usually here, usually you will need to quantify. You can do this. You can come up with this.
You can come up with P prime by
quantifying, by introducing a universal quantifier or something as simple as that.
Now that we're done with this, with the general idea, let's try and apply that to
an example. That example is the second problem in the large group tutorial
cheat. Prove that A is smaller than or equal to B and C is smaller than or equal to D.
So that if A is smaller than or equal to B and C is smaller than or equal to D, then
A multiplied by C is smaller than or equal to B multiplied by D. And I will tell you,
let's do that by induction on D. So we prove it by induction on D. So step number one,
what is P, okay? What is P which we are trying, the P that we're trying to prove is
the entire theorem statement, okay? So it is the whole thing. Not just the conclusion of
the theorem statement, but the entire theorem statement. So that is the P, okay? So
I'll write that there. So the P is that if given an A and the B and the C and the D,
if A is less than or equal to B and C is less than or equal to D, then A multiplied by C is smaller
than or equal to B multiplied by D, okay? First of all, that is the P, okay? Now, okay, so that's
step number one in our schema. Now apply step number one in this recipe, which is this step,
okay? Now we're in this step. So apply the induction schema. So basically, we say,
we try to find out what is the base case and what is the step case. So the base case is,
we're doing induction on D. So the base case will be P of zero. So P of zero. So
this zero we passed in as the value of D. So that is, so this is the base case. So P of zero,
which is equivalent to saying that we want to prove that A is smaller than or equal to B implies
C is smaller than or equal to zero implies A multiplied by C is smaller than or equal to B
multiplied by zero, okay? So the base case, to prove the base case, our first step is to say that
C equals zero, okay? And then I will write again our assumptions on the right here. So if
anything, if X is smaller than zero, then that implies X equals zero. So we have, let C is smaller
than or equal to zero. That implies that C equals zero. But let me just rewrite something before I
continue the proof. Let me just rewrite that. So I will just copy that and rewrite it in the form
of assumptions and the goal, okay? So what are the assumptions that we have here? The assumptions
that we have here are 1A smaller than or equal to B, 2C smaller than or equal to zero, okay? And
the goal is A is multiplied by C is smaller than or equal to B multiplied by zero, okay? So that is,
so I copied that and just simply rewrote it like this, okay? So from that we have
in the first step, C equals zero. This follows from lemma one and assumption two. And then
step number two, A multiplied by C equals zero. And again, this should follow from a lemma
saying that anything multiplied by zero equals zero. X multiplied by zero equals zero.
Sorry, so before I do that, we missed a smaller step. So A multiplied by zero equals zero from
lemma two and then 3A multiplied by C equals zero from step two and substituting one,
substituting step one, right? So substituting this, let C equals zero. And then four, we can say that
A multiplied by C is smaller than or equal to B multiplied by zero, which is our goal. Based on
the lemma, that should say any zero is smaller than or equal to any X, okay? So that is from
lemma number three, okay? So now let's go to the step case. What is the step case? Again,
the P, as I said, is the whole thing, is the whole theorem statement. So what is the step
case? Based on our recipe, is that if we have P of N, then from that we can get P of N plus one,
okay? N here is going to be the D, and N plus one is going to be the D plus one or suck D,
okay? So let me rewrite that. So basically what we want to prove is, if you have an A
that is smaller than or equal to B, sorry, an A that is smaller than or equal to C,
the theorem statement again, and a B that is, sorry, that's the theorem statement,
A is smaller than or equal to B, and C smaller than or equal to D, then we have A multiplied by
C smaller than or equal to B multiplied by D. That is P of N, which is the induction hypothesis.
And we want to show that if we have that, this implies, from that we can show that
A smaller than or equal to B, implies C smaller than or equal to D, implies A multiplied by C
smaller than or equal to B multiplied by the successor of D, okay? So that's the goal,
okay? And that this is P of N plus one, okay? P of suck N, okay? Okay. Now, again, I will write
that in the form of assumptions and a goal, okay? So what are our assumptions? So assumptions,
the first assumption is the induction hypothesis, which is that, so we'll just copy that, okay?
And the second assumption is that, is the assumption of that and the, sorry, and this one should be
suck D, because as I said, we want to prove, this is supposed to be the P of suck N, and N
is just the D here. So the second assumption is A smaller than or equal to B, and then the second,
and the third assumption should be the third assumption of our goal, the second assumption
of what we want to prove, which is C smaller than or equal to the successor of D. And the goal
is that we want to prove is that A multiplied by C is smaller than or equal to B multiplied by the
successor of D, okay? So now, let us prove it. So the proof, the first step of the proof,
we want to show that because C is more than or equal to the successor of D, then C minus one is
more than or equal to D, okay? So we want to just have C minus one is more than or equal to D, okay?
So we can get that by assuming a lemma here, which says that if I know that
A is more than or equal to the successor, not A and B, I'll just use X and Y so that it's clear
we're talking about general lemmas. So if X is more than or equal to the successor of Y, then X minus one
is more than or equal to Y, okay? So this should follow from lemma four and assumption three.
The second step here, okay, so now we want to apply the induction hypothesis.
So the induction hypothesis says that C is more than or equal to D, okay?
In order for us to apply the induction hypothesis, we need to show that the assumptions of the
induction hypothesis hold. We need to prove both of those assumptions. We only could prove that C
minus one is smaller than or equal to D. We could not prove that C is more than or equal to D,
right? We don't know that C is more than or equal to D. So in order for us to use this
induction hypothesis, we can use that to show that this assumption holds, but how can we show that
the second assumption holds? How can we do that? We cannot do that with this step that we have here,
which means that we cannot currently, we cannot apply this induction hypothesis. So remember,
let's go back to the simple schema that I gave you. So see if you can use the induction
hypothesis to prove the step, okay? If yes, then it's fine. If no, then we can try to find a more
general P. So we strengthen our P, usually by universally quantifying over some variable
that we cannot instantiate currently. So here, our problem is that we cannot instantiate
this C with C minus one, okay? We have here C minus one is more than or equal to D. We
cannot use that to prove that C, that C is more than or equal to the induction hypothesis,
right? So we need to strengthen, we need to generalise that assumption to be able to basically
use C minus one instead of C. How can we do that? It can simply be done by strengthening the P
and turning it into this universally quantified P, okay? So let me
just insert a P prime there. So copy all of that and give some space for the P prime, okay?
So as a stronger P prime, we need to get a stronger P prime. What is that? Stronger P prime? We can
just use a P prime where we quantify over the C. So if we turn our P prime into, if we turn our P
into that P prime, which is stronger, so if we can prove this second P prime with induction, then we
have proved the first one, because the second one is stronger than the first one, because
in the second one, we're quantifying for all Cs, while the first one, we're talking about
a specific C, so you can just instantiate the C of the first one. You can instantiate the
C of the P prime with the C of the P, if that makes sense. So if we do that and then we use this
P prime for our proof, then our base case will turn into a quantified base case. So it will be for
all C, we have that, and our step case, which is the more interesting thing, will turn into,
the induction hypothesis will turn into for all C. It's not equal to B implies C, okay? So we'll
copy it here, okay? So now we can instantiate, so now we can use the second, this assumption to
instantiate that, so this assumption to instantiate that, and this assumption to instantiate that by
saying that the C minus one goes in the place of C, because here we're saying for all Cs, okay?
So we can conclude that A multiplied by C minus one is smaller than or equal to B
multiplied by D from the induction hypothesis, and assumption to end step, right? Just forward,
normal forward reasoning, okay? Now, because, okay, now we want to say the following. We want to
get, we want to turn this into C, we want to turn this term into C,
so we want to transform that into C, and we want to transform that into successor of D.
So we can do that by, we basically, we need a lemma that says if A is, if A multiplied by
the successor of C minus one is smaller than or equal to B multiplied, sorry, let me just take that off,
this is not it. We want to say that if A multiplied by C minus, if A multiplied by C minus one
as written here is smaller than or equal to B multiplied by D, then from that we can conclude
that A multiplied by the successor of C minus one is smaller than or equal to B multiplied by the
successor of D, okay? So basically add one to the second term here and add one to the second term
there. This is not in general, so what is the lemma that allows us to do that? So let us
try to come up with the lemma that allows us to basically add the one here and the one there,
which would then help us go to that conclusion that we want, right? So let's add lemma five.
So lemma five is we want to say some, we want something that says that basically X multiplied
by the successor of Y is smaller than or equal L multiplied by the successor of M,
if X multiplied by Y is smaller than or equal to L multiplied by M and if X is equal to L. So that is
the lemma that we want, right? So then from this lemma, we get the following.
So from this lemma, we can get that A multiplied by the successor of C minus one is smaller than
equal to B multiplied by the successor of D. And where do we get that? This is from lemma number
five and assumption number two and step number two. Okay, so now the last step to show our goal
is we basically want to see if this is the same as C. We want to basically say that this is C.
As I said in the module tutorial and in my previous videos that minus is defined in the
following ways. The definition of minus, let me just write it there. The definition of minus is
as follows. So X minus Y is defined to be zero if X is smaller than or equal to Y and otherwise
it is defined to be, let me just write it in a different way. So if we'll just shuffle this.
So zero, just turn the zero into the second case. X minus Y equals X prime minus Y prime.
If X is greater than or equal to Y and if X equals the successor of X prime
and Y equals the successor of Y prime. Otherwise X is zero, otherwise X minus Y is zero. So it's zero
otherwise. What does that mean in our case? That means that basically minus behaves only normally
if X is greater than or equal to Y. So if X is greater than or equal to Y then it behaves normally.
If X is smaller than or equal to Y it always returns zero. So whenever you're proving something
about minus you have to take, you have to do your proof by case splitting. So here we then,
sorry, you have to do your proof by case splitting on whether X is greater than or equal to Y,
just to be clear. So here in our case the X is C and the Y is minus one. So the proof
by case is on whether C is greater than or equal to one. So the first step of that proof,
I will just continue. So this is one, two, three, and then step number four. So if C is greater than
or equal to one, from that I'll just call this minus definition. I'll just call this the
definition of minus. So from minus definition we know that from minus definition and
the assumption which is that C is greater than or equal to one, we know that C,
the successor of C minus one will just be C. The successor of C minus one is just C.
That is from minus definition case assumption. And then from that we say that we can conclude our
goal, which is that A multiplied by C is smaller than or equal to B multiplied by the successor
of D, and that should follow from three substituting four. And that is our goal,
right? So the goal is A multiplied by C is more than or equal to B multiplied by C.
The other case is, sorry, I should just say that this is case number one. Number two is that C
is not bigger than or equal to one. So that means that, again, I will start step number four,
because these are two branches of the proof. So step number four here would be that C is
strictly smaller than one from a lemma that says if something is not greater than or equal to
something else, then it's strictly smaller than it. So I'll just say that. So this should be lemma
six is not smaller than or equal to I, not greater than or equal to I, is not greater than or equal
to I. That implies that X is strictly smaller than Y. And lemma seven, if X is strictly smaller
than one, that means X is zero. So from lemma six, we know that. From lemma seven and step four,
we know that C is zero. And then the rest is like the base case. Because in the base case,
if you recall, we have proved that C equals zero there. And then the rest of the, and here
we also have the C equals zero. And then the rest of these steps can be used there.
So that's all for the proof. Thank you very much. I hope you have understood that. If you
have any questions, please let me know.